{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Rebel officers from this empire brutally killed 72 prominent intellectuals in another country in the Slaughter of the Knezes. This empire’s military defeated Uros the Weak at the Battle of Maritsa in 1371; eighteen years later, Prince Lazar and a leader of this opposing empire were each killed at the Field of Blackbirds. Murad I led this empire at the Battle of Kosovo. For ten points, name this Islamic power whose sultans controlled Serbia from Constantinople.",
      "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "A player of this instrument who died at a young age due to multiple sclerosis was married to conductor Daniel Barenboim. This is the main instrument of the founder of the Silkroad ensemble and arts non-profit. On the day that Soviet troops invaded Czechoslovakia to end the Prague Spring, Dvorak’s B minor concerto for this instrument was performed by Mstislav Rostropovich. Jacqueline du Pr´e and Yo-Yo Ma play, for ten points, what large string instrument?",
      "answer": "cello"
    },
    {
      "question": "A fleet of 49 ships on the victorious side of this battle was commanded by Charles Saunders. Members of the 78th Highlanders were able to make a surprise landing the night before this battle because one side was expecting a supply convoy. A general at this battle claimed that only 100 men were needed to guard L’Anse au Foulon. For ten points, name this battle in the Canadian theater of the Seven Years’ War where the Marquis de Montcalm and James Wolfe, the generals of the opposing sides, were both killed.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Quebec",
        "Battle of the Plains of Abraham"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man defeated incumbent New Deal opponent Roscoe Patterson in a 1934 Senate election. In one speech, this man acknowledged the success of a recent economic program that started with “16 free nations;” that speech supported the Marshall Plan, which had been signed into law by this man in 1948. For ten points, name this man who won the first presidential election after World War II and succeeded Franklin Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Harry Truman"
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem written during this period describes the sound of war vehicles as they approach the battle field; that poem is “The Song of Wagons.” Another poet during this period allegedly drowned after drunkenly trying to hug the reflection of the moon in a pond. Du Fu and Li Bai wrote during the rule of this dynasty, which faced the An Lushan Rebellion under Emperor Xuanzong. Empress Wu established the Second Zhou dynasty during, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty that existed between the Sui and Song dynasties?",
      "answer": "Tang Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to myth, a king named Tuu Ku Ihu moved these objects with the help of a fertility god. Many of these objects were toppled after they were discovered by Jacob Roggeveen. Several of these objects, which were often topped with a topknot structure called a pukao, are found at a site called Ahu Akivi. One of these objects at the British Museum is called Hoa Hakananai’a, and these objects were often set on stone platforms called ahu. The Rapa Nui people worshiped, for ten points, what stone heads on Easter Island?",
      "answer": "Moai statues"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ship’s second to last captain, Daniel Dow, resigned from stress after the Louis and Laverock failed to escort it. The Juno arrived too late to rescue this ship’s passengers, which included Alfred Vanderbilt. Failure to follow a zig-zag pattern may have led to this ship’s sinking. William Jennings Bryan resigned after the downing of this ship, which was carrying 50 tons of shell casings at the time it was destroyed in the North Atlantic. 128 Americans drowned on this ship. For ten points, the United States entered World War I after what ship was torpedoed by a U-Boat?",
      "answer": "RMS Lusitania"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group’s second and final leader was Robert Greim, who was appointed to his post after covertly traveling to Tiergarten with Hanna Reitsch. This force, which was greatly expanded by Walter Wever and Albert Kesselring, employed the Ju-87 in Spain as part of the Condor Legion that bombed Guernica. Operation Sealion was canceled when this group was defeated by the RAF in the Battle of Britain. Hermann Goring led, for ten points, what Nazi air force?",
      "answer": "Luftwaffe"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Matoa sank in this lake in a 1913 storm that killed over 200 sailors across nearly a dozen ships. This lake’s town of Goderich has been a salt mining center since the 1800s. This lake contains the Georgian Bay, which is bounded by the largest freshwater island in the world. Manitoulin Island and Saginaw Bay are in this lake, which the Saint Marys River feeds from Lake Superior. For ten points, name this American Great Lake that forms the northeastern border of Michigan.",
      "answer": "Lake Huron"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s administration is seen as the beginning of the American spoils system, because he replaced 919 officials upon election. This man supposedly declared “Marshall has made his decision, now let him enforce it” in response to the Supreme Court decision in Worcester v. Georgia. The Indian Removal Act was put into law by, for ten points, what seventh president of the United States?",
      "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader narrowly avoided capture at Drvar when he was targeted in Operation Knight’s Move. This leader had been forced to cooperate with Draza Mihailovic, the head of the Chetnik movement, in a guerrilla conflict. This European leader served as the first Secretary-General of the Non-Aligned Movement after he was expelled from Cominform by Joseph Stalin. This leader rose to prominence leading the Partisan movement in World War II. For ten points, name this marshal who led communist Yugoslavia.",
        "answer": [
          "Josip Broz Tito",
          "either",
          "both names"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tito was succeeded by this leader as Secretary-General of the Non-Aligned Movement in 1964.",
        "answer": "Gamal Abdel Nasser"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "V´ıctor Huggo Martin portrayed this man in a David Attwood miniseries a year after this man’s Untold Story was released as a documentary by Estela Bravo. Prior to his interviews with Hugo Chavez and Vladimir Putin, Oliver Stone released two documentaries of interviews with this man: a 2004 film Looking for him, and a 2003 film titled just Comandante. A 2006 BBC documentary reviewed the alleged 638 ways in which the CIA attempted to assassinate, for ten points, what longtime dictator of Cuba?",
        "answer": "Fidel Castro"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 2002 miniseries Fidel, Gael Garcia Bernal played what other revolutionary, a role that he reprised in the 2004 film The Motorcycle Diaries?",
        "answer": "Ernesto “Che” Guevara"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician’s chosen successor died in a stunt plane crash over his office in June 1980. This politician, who implemented a program of forced sterilizations, was eventually succeeded by a man who was assassinated in 1991 by the Tamil Tigers. After this politician authorized Operation Blue Star, her own Sikh bodyguards assassinated her in 1984. For ten points, name this first female Prime Minister of India.",
        "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Indira Gandhi’s oldest son died in the 1980 plane crash, and her second son became Prime Minister in 1984 and was killed in 1991. Name either son.",
        "answer": "Sanjay Gandhi and/or Rajiv Gandhi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The outcome of this conflict led Mark Twain to angrily write “The War Prayer.” During this conflict, Charles Eagan was criticized for poisoning troops by providing “embalmed beef.” The order “you may fire when ready, Gridley” was given during a decisive naval victory in this conflict during which one only American under George Dewey died. The yellow journalism of William Randolph Hearst fueled sentiment for, for ten points, what “splendid little war” that began after the Maine sank in Havana Harbor in 1898?",
        "answer": "Spanish-American War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Commanding General of the US Army led the criticism of the embalmed beef scandal during the Spanish-American War, less than a decade after his subordinate failed to handle what became the Wounded Knee Massacre.",
        "answer": "Nelson Miles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A politician with this last name used “unparliamentary language” while addressing John Lundrigan in the House of Commons in what became known as the “Fuddle Duddle” incident. Photos of another politician with this last name wearing blackface at an Arabian Nights gala surfaced in September of 2019; that politician’s party lost their majority in 2019 elections. For ten points, give this last name of Pierre and Justin, a father-son pair of Canadian Prime Ministers.",
        "answer": [
          "Trudeau",
          "Pierre and/or Justin Trudeau"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Both Trudeaus led this Canadian political party, which introduced universal healthcare in the late 1960s. This party lost its majority in the House of Commons to the Conservative Party in 2019.",
        "answer": "Liberal Party"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Early kings of these people like Euric conquered southern Gaul, defeated the Alans, and forced the Vandals into north Africa. The Gaullic possessions of this group were later taken by the Franks, and later kings like Roderic spent their time fighting each other, then lost their kingdom to the Moors. Rome was sacked in 410 AD by, for ten points, what barbarian tribe, the western branch of the Goths?",
        "answer": "Visigoths"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This first king of the Visigoths led the 410 sacking of Rome, but died in the same year.",
        "answer": "Alaric I"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A work in this medium, Cut with the Kitchen Knife, is one of the many Weimar-era works in this medium created by Hannah H¨och. That work in this medium shows General Hindenberg’s head pasted onto the body of a bellydancer, as well as a map of the European countries where women could vote, which had been cut out from a magazine. For ten points, name this artistic medium in which an artist assembles a single image from pieces of photographs.",
        "answer": [
          "photomontage",
          "composite imagery",
          "collage"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Photomontagist Hannah H¨och is the only woman officially included in the Berlin school of this art movement, which was characterized by embracing irrationality and satire. A popular legend says that it got its name at random from the dictionary.",
        "answer": [
          "Dadaism",
          "word forms like Dadaist"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This President was briefly served by Labor Secretary Martin Patrick Durkin, the “plumber” in his “eight millionaires and a plumber” Cabinet; the “millionaires” included Defense Secretary Charles E. Wilson, who was a former CEO of General Motors, and Secretary of State John Foster Dulles. During his presidential campaign, this man was pressured to keep his Vice Presidential candidate, despite allegations of a slush fund, after the Checkers speech. Richard Nixon ran on a ticket with, for ten points, what US President who succeeded Harry Truman?",
        "answer": "Dwight David Eisenhower"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Under Eisenhower, this Cabinet department was led by Oveta Culp Hobby, a former WAC leader who became the second female Cabinet member in history. You can give either its name prior to 1979 or its current name, which it got in 1979 when the Department of Education was split off.",
        "answer": [
          "Department of Health and Human Services",
          "HHS",
          "Department of Health, Education, and Welfare"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Boston Massacre",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State where it took place.",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future President who defended the accused soldiers.",
          "answer": "John Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "First casualty of the attack, a man not included in a famous Henry Pelham engraving of the event.",
          "answer": "Crispus Attucks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Boston silversmith who copied that Pelham engraving and, five years later, made a famous midnight ride.",
          "answer": "Paul Revere"
        },
        {
          "question": "British commander-in-chief who originally placed troops in Boston years earlier; he was replaced by General Howe in 1775.",
          "answer": "Thomas Gage"
        },
        {
          "question": "Street on which it took place.",
          "answer": "King Street"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician, the namesake of a college in Maine, who wrote A Short Narrative of the Horrid Massacre.",
          "answer": "James Bowdoin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Captain of the British soldiers during the massacre; he was acquitted because he did not give an order to fire.",
          "answer": "Thomas Preston"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Charlemagne",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Title he was given by Pope Leo III on Christmas, inspiring Otto I two centuries later.",
          "answer": [
            "Carolingian Emperor",
            "Roman Emperor",
            "Holy Roman Emperor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which he was given that title.",
          "answer": "800 AD"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Charlemagne’s Frankish realm.",
          "answer": "Aachen"
        },
        {
          "question": "People he conquered by defeating Desiderius.",
          "answer": "Lombards"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scholar from York who was invited to Charlemagne’s court.",
          "answer": "Alcuin of York"
        },
        {
          "question": "Frankish scholar who wrote the Vita Karoli Magni, a biography of Charlemagne.",
          "answer": "Einhard"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle where Charlemagne’s army was ambushed in the Pyrenees by Basque forces.",
          "answer": "Battle of Roncevaux Pass"
        },
        {
          "question": "LeaderofaSaxonrebellionagainstCharlemagnethatwasslaughteredatVerden;thismansurrendered and was baptized.",
          "answer": "Widukind"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Turmoil in Ancient Egypt",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Lover of Marc Antony and Julius Caesar whose death by snakebite effectively ended rule by Egyptian pharaohs.",
          "answer": "Cleopatra VII Philopator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Macedonian ruler who conquered Egypt and built a city named for him on the Nile delta.",
          "answer": "Alexander the Great or Alexander III of Macedon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pharoah who fought the Hittites at the Battle of Kadesh.",
          "answer": [
            "Ramesses the Great or Ramesses II",
            "Ozymandias"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City, sacked by Ashurbanipal in 663 BC, whose ruins are in modern Luxor near the Valley of the Kings.",
          "answer": "Thebes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Female Neoplatonist philosopher who was killed by an angry mob in 415 AD.",
          "answer": "Hypatia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mysterious group, including the Sherden, that attacked during the late Bronze Age collapse.",
          "answer": "Sea Peoples"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caliphate that conquered Egypt in 639; its name reflects the “rightly guided” nature of its four leaders.",
          "answer": "Rashidun Caliphate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Achaemenid king who conquered Egypt at the 525 BC battle of Pelusium; his brother Bardiya briefly succeeded him before Darius took over.",
          "answer": "Cambyses II"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This dynasty’s greatest ruler rose to power on the “Night of the Three Caliphs,” named because his son Mamun was born while the king Hadi died. This dynasty was established following a battle at the Great (20 pts)",
        "Zab in which its founder, as-Saffah, prevailed. A river allegedly ran black with ink from destroyed books after (10 pts)",
        "Hulagu Khan sacked this dynasty’s capital and desecrated the House of Wisdom that had been built by Harun al-Rashid. For ten points, name this caliphate that lasted until the 13th century in Baghdad."
      ],
      "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Many hypotheses about this event were strengthened by a 2016 project to drill into the only extant peak ring on Earth; the drilling found pink granite and shocked quartz. The (20 pts)",
        "Alvarez family studied this event and posed the most prominent hypothesis about its origins. This event is often known as the “K-T event” for the symbols for the eras of geologic time it separates. A (10 pts)",
        "meteor impact at what is now the Yucatan Peninsula probably caused, for ten points, what event that, roughly 66 million years ago, wiped out nearly all large reptiles on Earth?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cretaceous-Tertiary extinction event extinction event before “K-T” is mentioned",
        "descriptions of “the end of the dinosaurs”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One side in this battle was aided by domineering artillery fire from Combs’ Hill. Charles Lee was court-martialed for failing to secure a decisive outcome in this battle, which failed to prevent Henry (20 pts)",
        "Clinton from withdrawing to New York. During the second day of this battle, artilleryman William Hays collapsed of (10 pts)",
        "heatstroke and his wife, Mary Hays, took his place loading the cannon, a feat that is often conflated with her transporting water to soldiers. For ten points, name this 1778 Revolutionary War battle that spawned the myth of Molly Pitcher."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Monmouth Courthouse"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After being unable to succeed his father’s throne, this figure became King of Tiryns by swapping thrones with his cousin Megapenthes. When invading Greece, Xerxes the First claimed that the Persian people were descendants of this figure. This figure accidentally killed his grandfather, (20 pts)",
        "Acrisius, with a discus, as was prophesied. Using a body part from a previous victim, this figure killed the sea monster (10 pts)",
        "Cetus to rescue Andromeda. For ten points, name this Greek hero, who used an invisibility cap and Hermes’ sandals to kill Medusa."
      ],
      "answer": "Perseus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Carole Pateman argued that this concept leads to the patriarchal domination of women. A work titled for this concept claims that countries in hot climates are more likely to be monarchies and notes that the power of the state is split between the (20 pts)",
        "government and the people, who represent the general will. The line “Man is (10 pts)",
        "born free; and everywhere he is in chains” opens a work titled for, for ten points, what political relationship in which people agree to be ruled by the state, discussed in a namesake book by Jean-Jacques Rousseau?"
      ],
      "answer": "social contract"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this century, Ruy L´opez de Villalobos came up with the name for the Philippines. Juan de Sepu´lveda engaged in a debate at Valladolid over the definition of natural slavery with Bartolome de las Casas during this century. The (20 pts)",
        "Revolt of the Comuneros occurred in this century, during which Joanna the Mad’s son ruled. Holy Roman Emperor Charles (10 pts)",
        "V supported the Council of Trent during this century and funded the expedition of Ferdinand Magellan. For ten points, name this century that began eight years after the first voyage of Christopher Columbus."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "1500s",
        "16th century"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hannibal said either Alexander the Great or this king was the greatest commander the world had ever seen. This king met his final defeats at the Siege of Sparta and while intervening in a civil war in Argos, but is better known for fighting the (20 pts)",
        "Carthaginians in Sicily and the Romans in Tarentum. This man’s victory at the Battle of Asculum led him to state, “if we are (10 pts)",
        "victorious in one more battle with the Romans, we shall be utterly ruined.” For ten points, name this king of Epirus who lends his name to a victory won at too great a cost."
      ],
      "answer": "Pyrrhus of Epirus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was sued by the family of Rene Schneider after this man’s order to stand down led to the kidnapping and death of Schneider. This man was replaced by Brent Scowcroft as National Security Advisor during the “Halloween (20 pts)",
        "Massacre” in Gerald Ford’s cabinet. For his role in seeking a “peace with honor,” a Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to this man and (10 pts)",
        "Le Duc Tho, who declined the award. This man negotiated with Zhou Enlai to orchestrate a visit to Mao Zedong in China. For ten points, name this man who served as Richard Nixon’s Secretary of State."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry Kissinger"
    }
  ]
}